I have a daughter, Mulan.
لدى إبنة ، مولان.
And when she was eight, last year,
وعندما بلغت ثمانية أعوام، فى العام الماضى،
she was doing a report for school
كانت تعمل تقريراً للمدرسة،
or she had some homework about frogs.
أو كان لديها واجب منزلى عن الضفادع.
And we were at this restaurant,
وكنا فى ذلك المطعم.
and she said, "So, basically,
وقالت لى، " حسناً، فى الأساس،
frogs lay eggs
تضع الضفادع البيض
and the eggs turn into tadpoles,
ويتحول البيض إلى الشراغف،
and tadpoles turn into frogs."
وتتحول الشراغف إلى ضفادع."
And I said, "Yeah. You know, I'm not really up on my frog reproduction that much.
قلت لها، " أجل, أتعلمين، أنا لست على دراية كافية بتكاثر الضفادع.
It's the females, I think, that lay the eggs,
إنها الإناث، كما أعتقد، التى تضع البيض.
and then the males fertilize them.
ثم يقوم الذكر بتخصيبها.
And then they become tadpoles and frogs."
ومن ثم يصبحن شراغف و ضفادع."
And she says, "What? Only the females have eggs?"
وقالت لى، " ماذا؟ الإناث فقط تضع البيض؟"
And I said, "Yeah."
فقلت، " نعم."
And she goes, "And what's this fertilizing?"
فاضافت، "و ما هو التخصيب؟ "
So I kind of said, "Oh, it's this extra ingredient,
فقلت ، " "آه ، هذا هو عنصر اضافي،
you know, that you need
أتعلمين، نحتاجه
to create a new frog
فى تخليق الضفادع
from the mom and dad frog." (Laughter)
من الضفدع الأم و الضفدع الأب."
And she said, "Oh, so is that true for humans too?"
فقالت،" آه، وهل ينطبق ذلك على البشر أيضاً ؟"
And I thought, "Okay, here we go."
وفكرت، "حسناً، ها قد بدأنا."
I didn't know it would happen so quick, at eight.
لم أعتقد أنه سيحدث سريعاً، فى سن الثامنة.
I was trying to remember all the guidebooks,
كنت أحاول أن أتذكر كل كتب الإرشاد،
and all I could remember was,
وكل ما تمكنت من تذكره كان،
"Only answer the question they're asking.
" فقط أجب على الأسئلة التى يسألونها.
Don't give any more information." (Laughter)
ولا تعطى أى معلومات أخرى."
So I said, "Yes."
ولذلك رددت، " نعم."
And she said, "And where do, um,
فقالت لى، "و أين،
where do human women,
أين تضغ المرأة "البشر"،
like, where do women lay their eggs?"
أين تضع المرأة البيض؟"
And I said, "Well,
قلت، "حسناً
funny you should ask. (Laughter)
من الطريف أن تسألي.
We have evolved to have our own pond.
لقد تطورنا و أصبح لدينا بركة خاصة.
We have our very own pond inside our bodies.
لدينا بركة خاصة داخل أجسامنا.
And we lay our eggs there,
ونضع البيض هنالك.
we don't have to worry about other eggs or anything like that.
ليس علينا القلق حول بويضات أخرى أو أي شئ مثل ذلك.
It's our own pond. And that's how it happens."
إنها البركة الخاصة بنا. وذلك هو ما يحدث."
And she goes, "Then how do they get fertilized?"
فقالت، " إذاً كيف يتم تخصيبهم؟"
And I said, "Well,
فقلت لها، " حسناً،
Men, through their penis,
الرجال، عن طريق قضيبهم،
they fertilize the eggs by the sperm coming out.
إنهم يقوموا بتخصيب البويضات عن طريق الحيوانات المنوية التى تخرج منهم.
And you go through the woman's vagina."
وتذهب من خلال مهبل المرأة."
And so we're just eating, and her jaw just drops,
وكنا نأكل، فتدنى فكها،
and she goes, "Mom!
وقالت ، " أمي!
Like, where you go to the bathroom?"
كما عندما تذهبي إلى الحمام ؟ "
And I said, "I know.
فقلت، أعلم.
I know."
أعلم."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
That's how we evolved. It does seem odd.
هذة هي الطريقة التي تطورنا بها. إنها تبدو غريبة.
It is a little bit like having a waste treatment plant
إنها مثل وجود محطة لمعالجة النفايات
right next to an amusement park ...
بجوار منتزة تسلية.
Bad zoning, but ..." (Laughter)
سوء تقسيم المنطقة. ولكن ...
She's like, "What?" And she goes, "But Mom,
إنها مثل، " ماذا؟" و أضافت، ولكن يا أمي،
but men and women can't ever see each other naked, Mom.
الرجال و النساء لا يمكنهم رؤية بعضهم البعض عراة، يا أمي
So how could that ever happen?"
فكيف يمكن حدوث ذلك ؟ "
And then I go, "Well," and then I put my Margaret Mead hat on.
حينها وضعت قبعة مارغريت ميت.
"Human males and females
" الإنسان الذكور و الإناث
develop a special bond,
طوروا رابطة خاصة،
and when they're much older, much, much older than you,
وعندما يصحبوا أكبر فى السن، أكبر، أكبر بكثير من سنك الأن،
and they have a very special feeling,
ويكون لديهم مشاعر خاصة،
then they can be naked together."
حينها يمكنهم أن يكونوا عراة مع بعضهم البعض."
And she said, "Mom,
قالت لي، " أمي
have you done this before?"
هل قمت بفعل ذلك من قبل ؟"
And I said, "Yes."
قلت لها، " نعم."
And she said, "But Mom, you can't have kids."
قالت لي، " ولكن يا أمي، لا يمكنك إنجاب أطفال."
Because she knows that I adopted her and that I can't have kids.
لأنها تعلم أننى قمت بتبنيها وأننى لا يمكنني إنجاب أطفال.
And I said, "Yes."
قلت لها، " نعم."
And she said, "Well, you don't have to do that again."
فقالت لى، " حسناً، لا يجب عليك عمل ذلك مجدداً."
And I said, "..."
قلت لها، " ... "
And then she said, "But how does it happen when a man and woman are together?
وحينها قالت لي، " ولكن كيف يتم حدوث ذلك عندما يكون الرجل و المرأة معا ؟
Like, how do they know that's the time?
أعني، متى يعلموا أنه الوقت؟
Mom, does the man just say,
أمي، هل يقول الرجل فقط،
'Is now the time to take off my pants?'"
'هل حان الوقت لخلع سروالي؟"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And I said, "Yes."
رردت قائلة، " نعم."
"That is exactly right.
"إن ذلك صحيح تماماً.
That's exactly how it happens."
هذا هو بالضبط ما يحدث."
So we're driving home and she's looking out the window, and she goes,
وحينما كنا عائدين إلى المنزل بالسيارة، وكانت تنظر خارج النافذة، وقالت،
"Mom. What if two just people saw each other on the street,
" أمى، ماذا إذا رأى شخصان بعضهما البعض فى الشارع،
like a man and a woman, they just started doing it. Would that ever happen?"
رجل و إمرأة، وبدأوا بالقيام بذلك. هل يمكن حدوث هذا ؟"
And I said, "Oh, no. Humans are so private.
وقلت : "آه ، لا. البشر يحبوا الخصوصية جداً.
Oh ..."
آه لا."
And then she goes, "What if there was like a party,
قالت لي حينها، " ماذا إذا كان هنالك حفلة.
and there was just like a whole bunch of girls and a whole bunch of boys,
وكان هناك عدد من الأولاد وعدد من البنات.
and there was a bunch of men and women and they just started doing it, Mom?
وكان هناك عدد من الرجال و عدد من النساء و بدؤا في القيام بذلك، أمي ؟
Would that ever happen?"
" هل يمكن حدوث ذلك؟"
And I said, "Oh, no, no.
وقلت لها ، " آه، كلا، كلا .
That's not how we do it."
هذة ليست الطريقة التى نفعل بها ذلك."
Then we got home and we see the cat. And she goes,
وبعدها وصلنا إلى المنزل و رأينا القطة. فقالت لي إبنتي،
"Mom, how do cats do it?"
"أمي، كيف تقوم القطط بفعل ذلك؟ "
And I go, "Oh, it's the same. It's basically the same."
فرردت، " آه، نفس الشئ، إنها فى الأساس نفس الشئ."
And then she got all caught up in the legs. "But how would the legs go, Mom?
ومن ثم ركزت فقط فى الساقين. " ولكن كيف يمكن أن تتحرك الساقين ، أمي.
I don't understand the legs."
لا يمكننى أن أفهم الساقين."
She goes, "Mom, everyone can't do the splits."
وأضافت، " أمي، لا يمكن أن يفعل الجميع الإنقسامات."
And I go, "I know, but the legs ..."
فقلت لها، " أعلم، ولكن الساقين ..."
and I'm probably like, "The legs get worked out."
كنت مثل، " الساقين يتم التعامل معهم."
And she goes, "But I just can't understand it."
قالت، " ولكننى فقط لا أستطيع فهم ذلك."
So I go, "You know, why don't we go on the Internet,
فقلت حينها، " أتعلمين، لماذا لا نذهب إلى شبكة الإنترنت،
and maybe we can see ... like on Wikipedia." (Laughter)
وربما يمكننا رؤية ذلك..." على وكيبيديا مثلاً.
So we go online, and we put in "cats mating."
ولذلك ذهبنا على شبكة الإنترنت، وبحثنا عن تزواج القطط.
And, unfortunately, on YouTube, there's many cats mating videos.
ولسوء الحظ، على موقع يوتيوب، يوجد العديد من مقاطع فيديو لتزاوج القطط.
And we watched them and I'm so thankful,
وتفرجنا عليهم، و كنت شاكرة جداً،
because she's just like, "Wow! This is so amazing."
لأنها كانت مثل، " واو، إن هذا رائع حقاً."
She goes, "What about dogs?"
وقالت بعدها، " وماذا عن الكلاب؟"
So we put in dogs mating, and,
فبحثنا عن تزاوج الكلاب، و
you know, we're watching it, and she's totally absorbed.
أتعلمون، كنا نتفرج على ذلك، وكانت إستوعبت تماماً.
And then she goes, "Mom,
وقالت بعدها، " أمي
do you think they would have, on the Internet,
هل تعتقدين أن لديهم على شبكة الإنترنت،
any humans mating?"
تزاوج للإنسان ؟"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And then I realized that
وحينها أدركت
I had taken my little eight year old's hand,
أننى أخذت بأيدى طفلتى ذات الثمانية أعوام،
and taken her right into Internet porn. (Laughter)
إلى الأفلام الإباحية على شبكة الإنترنت.
And I looked into this
ونظرت إلى ذلك الوجه
trusting, loving face,
المحبب و الملئ بالثقة،
and I said,
وقلت،
"Oh, no.
"أوه ، لا.
That would never happen."
لا يمكن حدوث ذلك أبداً."
Thank you.
شكراً لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you. I'm so happy to be here.
شكراً لكم. أنا سعيدة جداً لوجودي هنا.